Guide to the James Kirkup Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1938-2007; Series II; 54.42; (135 boxes)
  - Works of Prose
    - Untitled Works
      - Essays on haiku and tanka, 1986-1996, undated (Box 100, Folder 906-908)
      - Japan: essays, typescripts and related material, 1989, undated (Box 100, Folder 909)
      - Essays and cuttings on translation, 1990s (Box 100, Folder 910)
      - Essays, Reviews (Atomic and Race), 1984, undated (Box 100, Folder 911)
      - Essays (Cowell, Pitter, etc.), drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 100, Folder 912)
      - Essays: Phallic Worship James Joyce's Zürich Ozu, etc., typescripts, undated (Box 100, Folder 913-914)
      - Essays on W. B. Yeats, typescript and holograph, and related clippings and ephemera, 1960s (Box 101, Folder 915)
      - Essays, typescript and copies of printed versions, undated (Box 101, Folder 916)
      - "Essays and notes on Feyaz Fergar," typescript and holograph, circa 1940 (Box 101, Folder 917-918)
      - "Kabuki - Utaemon," notes, drafts and related material, 1990s (Box 101, Folder 919)
      - Literary essays: European themes, typescripts, 1985-1989 (Box 101, Folder 920)
      - Introduction and materials for book by Mike Shields, 1996 (Box 101, Folder 921)
      - "Notes for review and translations", 1995 (Box 101, Folder 922)
      - Notes on books by Thomas Kirkup, undated (Box 101, Folder 923)
      - Articles by/about Kirkup, photocopies, undated (Box 101, Folder 924)
      - "Cuttings and Essays", undated (Box 101, Folder 925-926)
      - "Essays," drafts and offprints, 1970s, undated (Box 101, Folder 927)
      - Textbooks, drafts, typescript, correspondence and related material, 1980-1991 (Box 102, Folder 928-932)
      - "Some Japanese textbooks (Shakespeare, etc.)," page proofs, undated (Box 102, Folder 933)
      - [Untitled children's novel,] notes and drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 102, Folder 934)
      - High School Writing composition in Latin, holograph, undated (Box 102, Folder 935)
      - University papers, essays and notes, undated (Box 102, Folder 936-940)
  - Translations by James Kirkup
    Translations are organized under two headings: Works by a Single Author and Anthologies and Works by Multiple Authors.
    - Works by a Single Author
      Arranged alphabetically by author.
      - Apollinaire, Guillauma, Philippe Soupault, English translation by James Kirkup (fragment), typescript (copy), undated (Box 103, Folder 941)
      - Aragon, History of the U.S.S.R., English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1962? (Box 103, Folder 942)
      - Bartra, Carrera (Catalan Poets), English translations by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 103, Folder 943)
      - Baudelaire, Charles
        - English translations of poems by James Kirkup, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 103, Folder 944-945)
        - Mergen-Baudelaire Project, typescript and related material, undated (Box 103, Folder 946-947)
      - Boileau et Narojac, The Sleeping Beauty, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 103, Folder 948)
      - Boyland-Marsh, Sophie, Klabund, English translation by James Kirkup with related material, 1988 (Box 103, Folder 949)
      - Brecht, Bertold, Mother Courage And Her Children, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and copy, 1965, undated (Box 103, Folder 950)
      - Brecht, Bertold, Mother Courage and Her Children, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and copy (continued), 1965, undated (Box 104, Folder 951)
      - Celan, Paul
        - Fadensonnen, English translation by James Kirkup, with Words for Contemplation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 104, Folder 952)
        - Poems, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 104, Folder 953)
      - Charef, Mehdi, Alexina's House, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), undated (Box 104, Folder 954)
      - Christian, Paul, The History and Practice of Magic, English translation by James Kirkup, announcement, undated (Box 104, Folder 955)
      - Cliff, William, Poems, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts and related correspondence, 2000s (Box 104, Folder 956-957)
      - Deubel, Léon, Poetry, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 104, Folder 958)
      - d'Orleans, Charles, Poetry, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, 2002 (Box 104, Folder 959)
      - Drevet, Patrick
        - An Angel at Orsay, English translation by James Kirkup, typescripts and related correspondence, 1993 (Box 104, Folder 960-961)
        - My Micheline, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript carbon, printed version (copy) and related correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 105, Folder 962-964)
        - A Room in the Woods, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1990 (Box 105, Folder 965)
        - "Our Stores of Serenity," English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, 1996-1997 (Box 105, Folder 966-967)
        - "Auvers-sur-Oise," English translations by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 105, Folder 968)
        - "Patrick Drevet: Another Way of Seeing ," by Gervais Reed, typescript (copy), undated (Box 105, Folder 969)
        - Papers relating to Patrick Drevet translations (Box 105, Folder 970-975)
      - Dumitriu, Petru, To the Unknown God, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 106, Folder 976)
      - Dürrenmatt, Friedrich
        - The Anabaptists, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript carbon, undated (Box 106, Folder 977-978)
        - The Conformer, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (and copy), 1975 (Box 106, Folder 979-980)
        - Frank V, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1990 (Box 106, Folder 981)
        - Die Frist, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), 1976 (Box 106, Folder 982)
        - King John, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), undated (Box 106, Folder 983-984)
        - The Meteor, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript carbon, proofs and related material, 1973 (Box 107, Folder 985-986)
        - Period of Grace, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 107, Folder 987)
        - The Physicists, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and ephemera, 1963?, 1988 (Box 107, Folder 988-989)
        - Play Strindberg, author's proofs, 1973 (Box 107, Folder 990)
        - Portrait of a Planet, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related mateiral, 1971-1973 (Box 107, Folder 991-994)
        - Die Wiedertäufer, proofs, 1967 (Box 107, Folder 995)
        - [Various titles], drafts, clippings and ephemera, 1975-1976, undated (Box 108, Folder 996)
        - Clippings and other related material, 1975, undated (Box 108, Folder 997)
      - Gebhardt, Hertha von, The Girl from Nowhere, translated by James Kirkup, typescript and proof, 1958 (Box 108, Folder 998)
      - Glass, Julien, translations, notes and drafts, 1998 (Box 108, Folder 999)
      - Goldschmidt, Georges-Arthur
        - The Excluded, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related correspondence, 1993 (Box 108, Folder 1000)
        - Worlds of Difference, English translation by James Kirkup, printed version, corrected, 1991 (Box 108, Folder 1001)
        - Letters and reviews, undated (Box 108, Folder 1002)
      - Gracq, Julien, "Liberte Grande," English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1990s (Box 108, Folder 1003-1004)
      - Gréban, Arnoul and Simon
        - The True Mystery of the Nativity, adapted and translated by James Kirkup, typescript, 1955 (Box 109, Folder 1005)
        - The True Mistery of The Passion, English translation by James Kirkup
          - Drafts for radio and TV versions (BBC), typescript and galley proofs (OUP), and music for Nativity, undated (Box 109, Folder 1006-1008)
          - Drafts, holograph and typescript, and printed version, 1954, undated (Box 109, Folder 1009)
          - Drafts, reviews and ephemera, 1960s (Box 109, Folder 1010)
          - Proofs and associated material, 1977 (Box 109, Folder 1011)
          - Program, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 1012)
      - Guibert, Hervé
        - Des Aveugles ( Being Blind ), English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1995 (Box 110, Folder 1013-1014)
        - The Compassion Protocol, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1993 (Box 110, Folder 1015-1019)
        - Reviews of Kirkup's translations, undated (Box 111, Folder 1020)
      - Guidacci, Margherita, This Little Measure, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript drafts and printed version, undated (Box 111, Folder 1021)
      - Han-Shan, Cold Mountain Poems, interpreted by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1980, undated (Box 111, Folder 1022-1023)
      - Heininen, Paavo, The Damask Drum, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph, typescript and related material, 1984 (Box 111, Folder 1024)
      - Hojo, Nakajima, Songs of a Frog, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), undated (Box 111, Folder 1025)
      - Ibsen, Henrik
        - Brand (Oxford Ibsen), English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, clippings and correspondence, 1969 (Box 111, Folder 1026-1031)
        - Peer Gynt, English translation by James Kirkup, typescripts and related material, 1970s (Box 112, Folder 1032-1034)
        - Peer Gynt, English translation by Christopher Fry, proof, undated (Box 112, Folder 1035)
        - Peer Gynt, programs and reviews, 1970s (Box 112, Folder 1036-1037)
      - Jelloun, Tahar Ben, State of Absence, typescript carbon, 1994 (Box 112, Folder 1038)
      - Kästner, Erich, The Little Man, English translation by James Kirkup, publisher's typescript and associated material, 1966-1968 (Box 113, Folder 1039)
      - Kawabata, Yasunari, different versions and comments on translations by James Kirkup and Michio Nakano, 1998 (Box 113, Folder 1040)
      - Kervern, Alain, Selected Haiku, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, notes and correspondence, 1993-1997 (Box 113, Folder 1041)
      - Kleist, Heinrich von
        - Michael Kohlhaas, English translation by James Kirkup, proofs, circa 1968 (Box 113, Folder 1042)
        - The Prince of Homburg, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1958 (Box 113, Folder 1043-1044)
        - The Prince of Homburg, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph, undated (Box 113, Folder 1045)
        - The Prince of Homburg, reviews, correspondence and ephemera, 1970s (Box 113, Folder 1046)
      - Lagesse, Marcelle, The Diligence Departs at Dawn, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript carbon, undated (Box 113, Folder 1047)
      - Lamartine, Alphonse de, The Crucifix, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy) and related correspondence, 1952 (Box 113, Folder 1048)
      - Laye, Camara
        - Guardian of the Word, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, undated (Box 114, Folder 1049-1050)
        - The Radiance of the King, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1970 (Box 114, Folder 1051-1052)
      - Leclercq, Gine Victor, My Friend Carlo, English translation by James Kirkup, page proofs, 1969 (Box 114, Folder 1053)
      - Levi, Jean, La Mission, English translations by James Kirkup, typescript, with related correspondence, 1995 (Box 114, Folder 1054)
      - Linna, Väinö, The Unknown Soldier, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1957 (Box 114, Folder 1055)
      - Longs, Pierre, The Adventures of King Panpoleas, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph, undated (Box 114, Folder 1056)
      - Luzi, Mario
        - "L'Honore del Vero," English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy) and related material, undated (Box 114, Folder 1057)
        - Poems translated by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, undated (Box 114, Folder 1058)
      - Martin-Chauffier, S., The Other One, English translation by James Kirkup, page proofs, 1961 March 21 (Box 115, Folder 1059)
      - Michaux, Henri (Box 115)
        - For Putting Out Devils, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1946, undated (Box 115, Folder 1060-1062)
        - "Miscellaneous Types.," notes and drafts, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 115, Folder 1063)
      - Michiko, Ishimure, Pure Land Poisoned Sea, English translation by James Kirkup, printed version, 1987, undated (Box 115, Folder 1064)
      - Monenembo, Tierno, The Bush Toads, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript carbon, printed version, and related correspondence, 1981, undated (Box 115, Folder 1065-1067)
      - Mutsuo, Takahashi
        - Poems, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, holograph and typescript, 1989, undated (Box 116, Folder 1068)
        - Myself as an Anatomical..., English translation by James Kirkup and Tamaki Makoto, typescript (copy) and related material, undated (Box 116, Folder 1069)
      - Niel, Jean-Baptiste
        - Painted Shadows, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1987 (Box 116, Folder 1070-1071)
        - Painted Shadows, English translation by James Kirkup, "rough carbon", circa 1987 (Box 116, Folder 1072)
        - Ludion D'Alcool, printed version, 1990 (Box 116, Folder 1073)
      - Pancrazi, Jean-Noël
        - Vagabond Winter / Winter Quarters, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1992 (Box 117, Folder 1074-1075)
        - Reviews of Vagabond Winter, clippings and correspondence, 1992 (Box 117, Folder 1076)
        - Notebook: Jean-Noel Pancrazi, Winter Quarters, undated (Box 117, Folder 1077)
      - Perrin, André
        - Mario, English translation by James Kirkup, printed version (copy) and excerpts translated by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), undated (Box 117, Folder 1078-1079)
        - Michel's Room (A dramatic treatment of André Perrin's L'Indifférant ), holograph, 1992 (Box 117, Folder 1080)
        - Michel's Room, A dramatic treatment of André Perrin's L'Indifférent, typescripts (and copy), 1995, undated (Box 117, Folder 1081-1084)
        - Le Père, printed version (copy), undated (Box 118, Folder 1085)
      - Quiguard, Pascal, All the World's Mornings, English translation by James Kirkup, drafts, review and related material, 1991 (Box 118, Folder 1086-1087)
      - Racine, Jean, Andromaque, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), undated (Box 118, Folder 1088)
      - Rassmussen, Knud, "Tale of the Whale and His Soul," English translation by James Kirkup, typescript (copy), 2000s (Box 118, Folder 1089)
      - Rigaudis, Marc
        - Unidentified, translations by James Kirkup, drafts and related material, 1990, undated (Box 118, Folder 1090)
        - Ito-san, English translation by James Kirkup, printed versions of original and translation, accompanied by letters from Rigaudis to Kirkup, 1990-1991 (Box 118, Folder 1091-1093)
        - Photographs for Ito-san, undated (Box 118, Folder 1094)
        - Stories, computer printout (copy), 1990? (Box 119, Folder 1095)
      - Roubaud, Jacques, poems, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and copy, 1993, undated (Box 119, Folder 1096-1098)
      - Robiquet, Jean, Daily Life in the French Revolution, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1964 (Box 119, Folder 1099)
      - Saba, Umberto, and Powese, Poems, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 119, Folder 1100)
      - Sato, Satoru, "The little man who fell from the moon," English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 119, Folder 1101)
      - Schiller, Friedrich von, Don Carlos, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, 1971 (Box 119, Folder 1102)
      - Strindberg, August, The Dance of Death / Strindberg Without Tears, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph and related ephemera, 1970 (Box 119, Folder 1103-1104)
      - Supervielle, Jules
        - "Chaos and Creation" and other stories, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 119, Folder 1105)
        - The Child-Stealer, English translation by James Kirkup, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 119, Folder 1106-1108)
        - Poems, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 120, Folder 1109)
        - The Precipice of Light: Poems by Jules Supervielle, English translation by James Kirkup, partial typescript, undated (Box 120, Folder 1110)
        - Selected Writings of Jules Supervielle, English translations by James Kirkup, typescript and proof, undated (Box 120, Folder 1111-1112)
      - Takagi, Kyozo, Poems, English translations by James Kirkup and Michio Nakano, notes, drafts and related correspondence, 1990s (Box 120, Folder 1113-1114)
      - Tanzberg, Kris, Poems, English translations by James Kirkup, typescript and associated material, undated (Box 120, Folder 1115-1116)
      - Teuschl, Rainer, Poems and letters, English translations by James Kirkup, typescript and related material, 1994 (Box 120, Folder 1117-1118)
      - Thai, Vinh, Ancestral Voices, English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 121, Folder 1119)
      - Tsutsui, Yasutaka, Day Soldier, English translation by James Kirkup and Michio Nakano, typescripts and printouts, undated (Box 121, Folder 1120-1121)
      - Valery, Paul
        - Valery, Paul, The Eternal Virgin, English translation by James Kirkup, notes and typescript, undated (Box 121, Folder 1122)
        - Valery, Paul, "Life In Death," English translation by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 121, Folder 1123)
    - Anthologies and Works by Multiple Authors
      Arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
      - "Arab Translations"
        Notes, drafts, clippings and correspondence related to Kirkup's translation of Arab-French poetry.
        - "Arab Culture Translations", 2000s (Box 122, Folder 1124-1125)
        - Translations from Kadhim Jihad, 2000s (Box 122, Folder 1126)
        - Salah Stétié poems, undated (Box 122, Folder 1127)
        - Maram al-Masri poems, 1997-1998 (Box 122, Folder 1128)
        - Mohammed Bennis (poems and essays), 1999 (Box 122, Folder 1129-1131)
        - Abdel-Illah Salhi poems, 1998 (Box 122, Folder 1132)
        - Amina Saïd poems, undated (Box 122, Folder 1133)
        - Mustafa Nisabouri, 1999 (Box 122, Folder 1134)
        - Mustafa Nisabouri (continued), 1999 (Box 123, Folder 1135)
        - Ahmed Abodehman, "The Belt", 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1136-1138)
        - Saadi Youssef poems, 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1139)
        - Mohammed Dib, 1999 (Box 123, Folder 1140)
        - Tahar Ben Jelloun Selected Poems, 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1141)
        - "Adonis", 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1142)
        - Kadar Boubekri, 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1143)
        - Adnan Mohsen, 2000 (Box 123, Folder 1144)
        - Mehdi Charef, "Alexina's House", undated (Box 123, Folder 1145)
        - Mohammed Khaïr-Eddine, 2001 (Box 123, Folder 1146-1147)
        - "Arabo - Andalusian translated poems," typescript (copy) (Box 123, Folder 1148)
      - Atlas Press, drafts, correspondence and associated material, 1988-1993 (Box 123, Folder 1149)
      - The Bread of the Damned (An anthology of French decadent poetry, chosen and translated by James Kirkup), typescript, undated (Box 123, Folder 1150)
      - Brindin Press, printouts of virtual books, 2000s (Box 124, Folder 1151-1159)
      - A Certain State of Mind (An anthology of modern Japanese haiku selected and translated by James Kirkup), typescript and related material, 1990s (Box 124, Folder 1160-1163)
      - Chinese poetry translations, typescript carbon and copy, undated (Box 125, Folder 1164-1165)
      - Dutch poetry translations, drafts and related material, 1995 (Box 125, Folder 1166)
      - Espriu and others. Poems from Catalan, English translations by James Kirkup, typescript, undated (Box 125, Folder 1167)
      - French poetry translations, computer printout, undated (Box 125, Folder 1168)
      - French prose translation exercise, holograph, 1939-1940 (Box 125, Folder 1169)
      - French and German poetry translations, typescript and holograph, undated (Box 125, Folder 1170-1171)
      - Haiku translations, typescript, undated (Box 125, Folder 1172-1173)
      - Haiku and Tanka translations, typescript, 1992, undated (Box 126, Folder 1174)
      - Haiku translations / essay on Basho, holograph, 1994 (Box 126, Folder 1175)
      - Haiku and Tanka and Tamaki, translated by James Kirkup, typescripts and associated material, 1992 (Box 126, Folder 1176)
      - One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets (Hyakunin isshu), English translation by James Kirkup and Makoto Tamaki, typescript, manuscript, and related materials, undated (Box 126, Folder 1177-1178)
      - Japanese poetry, 1980, undated (Box 126, Folder 1179-1182)
      - Modern Japanese Poems (with some haiku) and Nakajima Hojo tanka, typescript, undated (Box 127, Folder 1183)
      - Selected Japanese short stories, English translation by James Kirkup, printed version (copy), undated (Box 127, Folder 1184)
      - Student translation exercises, undated (Box 127, Folder 1185)
      - "Symbolist/ Decadent (Patrick McGuiness)," drafts and related material, 2000s (Box 127, Folder 1186-1196)
      - True Tanka. English translation by James Kirkup, typescript and copy, and related material, 1996, undated (Box 127, Folder 1197-1200)
      - Victims and Tormenters, typescript and notes, 2000s, undated (Box 128, Folder 1201-1203)
  - Drama, Opera and Music
    - An Actor's Revenge
      - Typescript accompanied by correspondence and ephemera, 1975, undated (Box 129, Folder 1204)
      - Score, manuscript and printed version (copies), undated (Box 129, Folder 1205)
      - Clippings, reviews and ephemera, 1979-1980s (Box 129, Folder 1206-1207)
    - Behold! The Bridegroom!
      See also: Ghost Mother
      - Drafts, holograph and typescript (copy), 1951?, 1996 (Box 129, Folder 1208)
      - Typescripts, with other short play scripts, undated (Box 129, Folder 1209-1211)
      - New tanka version, typescript and copies, undated (Box 129, Folder 1212)
    - The Blue Flower: A Dance Drama in Verse, typescript, undated (Box 130, Folder 1213)
    - Buaku, typescript, undated (Box 130, Folder 1214)
    - Candle in the Heavens, typescript and related correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 130, Folder 1215)
    - Cloak of Feathers, typescript (copy), undated
      See also: Behold! The Bridegroom!
    - Cyrano de Bergerac, ephemera and clippings, 1974 (Box 130, Folder 1216)
    - The Disappearing Boy, typescript (copy), undated
    - Do You Come Here Often?, drafts, holograph and typescript (copy), 1995 (Box 130, Folder 1217-1218)
    - Don Carlos, production of version at Everyman Theatre: reviews, 1975 (Box 130, Folder 1219)
    - Emotional Songs, musical settings by David Schingh, copy of manuscript, 1984 (Box 130, Folder 1220)
    - Friends in Arms ("Achilles") (opera libretto)
      - Typescript accompanied by ephemera and correspondence, 1970s (Box 130, Folder 1221)
      - Manuscript (copy), undated
    - Ghost Mother, holograph and typescript, 1996 (Box 130, Folder 1222-1223)
      Includes Behold, the Bridegroom!, typescript
    - The Hero Gilgamesh, holograph, typescript typescript carbon, and typescript (copy), 1977, 2007 (Box 130, Folder 1224-1226)
    - Kastor and Polydeukes, typescript, undated (Box 131, Folder 1227)
    - The Lady of the Camelias, Adapted by James Kirkup from the novel and play by Alexandre Dumas, holograph and typescript, undated (Box 131, Folder 1228-1229)
    - The Magic Drum
      - Draft, holograph, undated (Box 131, Folder 1230)
      - Typescript, 1977 (Box 131, Folder 1231)